Guide to the Linda Dahl Collection on Mary Lou Williams, 1944-1993 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Linda Dahl Collection on Mary Lou Williams 1944-1993 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Dahl, Linda, 1949-
0.6 Linear Feet 375 Items
Author Linda Dahl wrote the first full-length biography of jazz pianist, arranger, composer, and educator Mary Lou Williams (1910-1981), titled Morning Glory: A Biography of Mary Lou Williams (1999).
The Linda Dahl Collection on Mary Lou Williams contains materials compiled by Dahl in researching the Williams biography, including newspaper and magazine clippings, correspondence, photographs and transparency strips, concert programs, and a variety of financial and foundation records.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Linda Dahl Collection on Mary Lou Williams was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2002.
Biographical and Historical Note
Author Linda Dahl wrote the first full-length biography of jazz pianist, composer, arranger, and educator Mary Lou Williams, titled Morning Glory: A Biography of Mary Lou Williams (New York: Pantheon Books, 1999). By the 1930s, Williams (born Atlanta, 8 May 1910; died Durham, N.C., 28 May 1981) had begun working as a pianist and/or arranger for bandleaders including Andy Kirk, Duke Ellington, Benny Goodman, and Dizzy Gillespie. Williams gained additional acclaim as a leader of her own bands as well as a composer of such works as Zodiac Suite (1946) and Music for Peace (1971), also known as Mary Lou's Mass. She was an artist in residence in Duke University's Department of Music from 1977-1981.
Collection Overview
The Linda Dahl Collection on Mary Lou Williams contains materials compiled by Dahl in researching her 1999 biography of Williams. The collection features newspaper and magazine clippings on Williams; letters from Williams to her friend Joyce Breach regarding Williams's concert tours and other travels, Roman Catholicism, the business of jazz, and Williams's medical ailments; as well as letters to Breach from other of Williams's associates. One folder of miscellaneous correspondence by Williams primarily relates to the planning of jazz concerts and to Williams's work with the Bel Canto Foundation and the Charlie Parker Memorial Fund. The collection also contains a selection of records related to the Mary Lou Williams Foundation; thirteen photographs and four transparency strips of Williams; a folder of concert programs featuring Williams or her compositions; and six miscellaneous publications, primarily on music, from throughout Williams's lifetime.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
African American Catholics
African American musicians -- Correspondence
Bel Canto Foundation
Breach, Joyce
Catholic Church -- United States
Clippings
Concert tours
Dahl, Linda, 1949-
Dahl, Linda, 1949-. Morning glory
Duke University. Dept. of Music. Faculty
Jazz
Jazz -- 1931-1940
Jazz -- 1941-1950
Jazz -- 1951-1960
Jazz -- 1961-1970
Jazz -- 1971-1980
Jazz musicians
Jazz musicians -- Health and hygiene
Mary Lou Williams Foundation
Photographs
Pianists -- United States
Programs
Transparencies
Williams, Mary Lou -- 1910-1981
Women jazz musicians -- United States
Related Material
Mary Lou Williams Collection
Institute of Jazz Studies, John Cotton Dana Library, Rutgers University
Contents of Collection
- Linda Dahl Collection on Mary Lou Williams, 1944-1993 and undated
  - Articles on African-American Music (Box 1)
  - Biographical Information
  - Concert Programs, 1944-1982
  - Documentary Film Research Files
  - Early Jazz Greats Information Cards
  - Last Will and Testament
  - Letters from Williams and associates to Joyce Breach, 1964-1981
  - Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, 1957-1993
  - Mary Lou Williams Foundation, Records and Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence from Williams, 1955-1969
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1959-1981 (2 folders)
  - Photographs and Transparencies